Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
The average adult uses nine
personal care products a day
and each of these products can have
hundreds of chemical ingredients.
And don't get me started on
mad cow disease intestines.
Here’s our first story.
The Food and Drug
Administration recently
reopened comments about
their policy of allowing some
intestines, but not others,
into the U.S. food supply.
When the first few cases
of mad cow disease started
popping up, the FDA's gut
reaction was to ban all guts
from food and personal care
products, but in 2005,
USDA and FDA amended their draft
rule to "permit the use of the
entire small intestine
for human food"
if the last 80 uncoiled inches going
to the colon was removed.
Since then, though, studies
have shown that infectious
mad cow prions can be found
throughout all parts of the
intestine, from the stomach
down to the cow's colon,
raising the question of
whether all entrails should
again be removed.
The North American Meat
Association says, NO, wanting
to keep all cattle insides
inside the food supply,
similar to what we heard
from the CTFA,
the Cosmetic, Toiletry,
and Fragrance Association.
They protested that
by banning from cosmetics
downer and dead
cattle, as well as brain,
skull, eyes, and spinal cords,
as well as intestines, and tonsils,
our nation's supply of cosmetics
could be put in jeopardy.
There could be a tallow
shortage for soap, for example.
The FDA may not realize that
cosmetics and personal care products
are a quarter trillion dollar
industry worldwide.
In the end, the FDA
tentatively concluded that
intestines should continue
to be allowed in the food and
cosmetic supply, because only
trace amounts of infectivity
have been found throughout
the bowels of cattle,
a conclusion they have to
make since otherwise,
all meat would have
to banned as well,
because new research shows
that mad cow infectivity
is in the muscles too.
And, not just the atypical
cases of BSE
like the last mad cow
found in California,
but now we know
the typical BSE as well,
Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy -
mad cow disease.
Low levels of infectious prions
found in the ribs, shoulders,
tenderloins, sirloin tips, and
round cuts of meat.
The latest estimates out of
Britain suggest 15,000 people
are currently incubating the
human form of mad cow disease,
contracted through the
consumption of infected meat.
Fewer than 200 Brits have
died so far of variant
Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, but
the incubation period for this
invariably fatal
neurodegenerative disease,
can be decades,
the time between eating the meat
and one's brain filling up with holes.
The fact that so many people
are carrying it has important
implications for the safety of
blood transfusions-
that's why many Americans
who've lived in England
are barred by the Red Cross
from donating blood,
as well as the safety of
handling surgical instruments
that may have cut
into someone who's a carrier,
since it's so hard to sterilize
anything once contaminated.
Given these factors, it may be
prudent to err on the side of
caution when regulating which
intestines are allowed
on and in our mouths.
But it's a balance.
As one meat company points
out, guts are not just used
for lipstick, intestines is
human food, "providing us with
a precious source of protein
which is evidently essential
for our human population."
In our next story, dozens
of lipsticks and lip glosses
are put to the test
for lead contamination.
Over the past years, the
use of cosmetic products
has evidently increased
at an alarming rate
due to unending pursuit for
individual beautification.
Nothing necessarily wrong
with that unless cosmetic products
contained ingredients that
may be linked to disease.
Ingredients, such as toxic
heavy metals like lead.
Lead has been found in a wide
range of cosmetic products,
from eye shadow to skin
cream, foundation, blush.
I talked about henna before…
but looking at the data,
an important warning
can be recognized—
the presence of lead in lipsticks—
because you end up inadvertently
actually swallowing a
little bit of it.
It has been estimated that a woman
may end up ingesting three pounds
of lipstick over her lifetime.
Moreover, lipsticks can be
used by pregnant women
or women of child bearing age.
Uh, duh.
Yes, lead is highly toxic,
but how much lead
can there be in lipstick?
Surely, it’s a very minor source.
Nonetheless, one should
not exclude the fact
that lead accumulates
in the body over time,
and so repetitive lead-
containing lipstick application
might lead to significant exposure.
But, you don’t really know…
until you put it to the test.
Thirty-two lipsticks and
lip glosses tested,
and lead was detected in
three-fourths of the products
suggesting public health concerns.
But how much lead did they find?
About half exceeded the FDA-
recommended maximum level
set for candy.
Yeah, but come on.
That limit is set for something
kids may eat every day.
Kids are not going to eat
tubes of lipstick every day.
Nevertheless, it's generally accepted
that there's no safe
level of lead intake;
ideally, we should get
contaminant levels down to zero.
And look, as a consumer
group pointed out,
a quarter of the lipsticks
were lead-free,
so we know it can be done.
So, maybe we should better
regulate toxic metals
in cosmetics to protect women’s
health in the United States,
as has already been
done in Europe.
Fair enough.
The billion-dollar lipstick
industry, however, wasn’t happy.
In an article that tried
to downplay the risks,
the scientists-for-hire firm
that once played villain
in the real-life Erin Brockovich case,
concluded that although
lipstick may contain lead,
the concentrations are so
low that they would not
be expected to pose any health
risks to adults or children.
Children’s blood lead
levels are influenced more
by background lead exposures
(in the air/dust/water/food)
than by lipstick exposures.
Ok, but just because our
environment is so contaminated
doesn’t mean we need
to add to the problem.
In fact, because there’s so
much lead around anyway,
maybe it’s that much more reason
to cut down on additional exposures,
but they calculate that an adult
would need to apply lipstick
over 30 times a day to raise
their blood lead level
to even the most stringent limits,
and 695 times a day
to get blood levels
up to more concerning levels.
Ah, but this was based on
an assumption that lipstick
would only have about one
part per million lead,
or at the extreme end
maybe two or three.
But by 2016, about ten times
more lipsticks were tested,
and they averaged nearly
500 parts per million,
with 10 percent over 1,000,
all the way up to 10,000
with more than one out
of five exceeding FDA
and even Chinese safety
limits on lead in cosmetics.
Lip gloss was worse than lipstick,
orange and pink had more lead
than brown, red, or purple,
and all the really contaminated
ones were the cheaper
ones, under five bucks.
But wait a second, 10,185 milligrams?
That’s 10 grams per kilogram,
which means the lipstick was
1 percent pure lead.
That means a single application
could expose a grown woman
to perhaps 12 times
the tolerable daily intake.
And if she’s interested
in having children,
then that poses a
particular concern,
as lead accumulates in your bones
and may then be released into
the bloodstream during pregnancy,
where it can slip through the
placenta or into the breastmilk.
The good news is that the FDA
is considering lowering
the maximum allowable lead
levels in lipstick from 20 to 10,
something Canada arrived
at a decade ago.
But without enforcement,
it doesn’t matter.
Moving the legal limit
from 20 down to 10
would just mean that instead
of 23 percent of lip products
exceeding legal levels 27 percent
would be exceeding legal levels.
Finally today, we ask,
is there risk of lead
and PPD contamination
of red and black henna?
Over recent decades,
we've started to recognize
that some topically applied substances
can penetrate into or even through
human skin and end up
circulating throughout our bodies.
Take the toxic heavy metal
lead, for example.
To see if lead could be absorbed
through the skin into the body,
researchers applied lead
to someone's left arm,
and then they measured the level of lead
in the sweat coming off their right arm
over the next few days, and
there was a big spike,
proving, nearly 30 years ago, that lead
can be absorbed through the skin
and rapidly distributed
throughout the body.
This led public health authorities
to recommend parents
avoid using cosmetics, at least on their
children, that could be contaminated.
Which cosmetics might those be?
Lead has been found in a wide
range of cosmetic products
because it's a natural constituent
of many color pigments.
The FDA has set an upper limit
for lead at 20 parts per million,
and though only some samples
of henna exceeded that—
because henna is used
for temporary tattoos—
these quantities of lead can
remain on the skin for a long time
and may not be safe.
Because studies show that lead may
have no identifiable safe exposure level
with even the lowest levels shown to
affect the brains of developing children,
thus the use of henna,
especially among children,
may constitute a public health risk.
So increasing awareness of henna's
serious toxic implications may help
end or at least reduce the use
of such hazardous materials,
especially when children are involved.
Now traditionally, henna was just the
dried powdered leaves of some plant.
But more recently, other ingredients have
been added to give it a stronger color,
added ingredients such as lead,
one of the most common and
egregious additives in henna.
But not as common as PPD,
para-phenylene-diamine.
The red paste traditionally
used, known as "red henna,"
rarely produces adverse effects.
But to achieve a darker pigment,
known as "black henna,"
various additives may be
used including animal urine,
but better pee than PPD,
a coal tar derivative that can cause
nasty skin reactions such
as blistering and scarring.
PPD is added to speed up the
process from as long as 12 hours,
down to less than 2 hours.
So while the use of black
hennas may be tempting,
it has the potential for both short-
and long-term side effects.
How common are these reactions?
The best estimate is about 2.5%,
so 1 in 40 kids that gets a black henna
tattoo may have an allergic reaction.
Unfortunately, this practice has become
fashionable (thanks a lot, Spice Girls).
There's no such thing
as natural black henna,
so perhaps it would best to respect
the more traditional practices,
lest a temporary tattoo
turns into a permanent scar.
The problem is that PPD can be found
in products labeled as red henna too,
so just because it's red
doesn't mean it's not risky.
Bad news for the $100 million industry.
Because henna of all colors
is so often adulterated,
under FDA guidelines, henna
shouldn't be applied to the skin at all.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.